I am an engineering professor,
أنا بروفيسور في الهندسة،
and for the past 14 years
وطوال الأربعة عشر عاما الماضية
I've been teaching crap.
كنت أُدرّس المخلفات.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Not that I'm a bad teacher,
ليس لأنني أستاذ سيء،
but I've been studying and teaching
ولكنني كنت أدرس وأُدرس
about human waste
عن المخلفات البشرية
and how waste is conveyed
وكيف تتم معالجة المخلفات
through these wastewater treatment plants,
عن طريق محطات معالجة مياه الصرف الصحي هذه،
and how we engineer and design
وكيف نهندس ونصمم
these treatment plants so that we can protect
هذه المحطات حتى نستطيع حماية
surface water like rivers.
المياه السطحية مثل الأنهار.
I've based my scientific career
لقد أسست مسيرتي العلمية
on using leading-edge molecular techniques,
على استخدام التقنيات الجزيئية الرائدة،
DNA- and RNA-based methods
أساليب حمض الديوكسي ريبونيوكليك والحمض الريبي النووي
to look at microbial populations in biological reactors,
للنظر إلى الأعداد الميكروبية في المفاعلات البيولوجية،
and again to optimize these systems.
ومرة أخرى لتحسين هذه النظم.
And over the years,
وعبر السنين،
I have developed an unhealthy obsession with toilets,
أصبح عندي هوس غير صحي مع المراحيض،
and I've been known to sneak into toilets
وقد عُرف أنني أتسلل إلى المراحيض
and take my camera phone
ومعي كاميرا هاتفي
all over the world.
في جميع أنحاء العالم.
But along the way, I've learned
ولكن على طول الطريق، تعلمت
that it's not just the technical side,
أنه ليس فقط الجانب التقني،
but there's also this thing called the culture of crap.
ولكن هناك أيضا هذا الشيء يسمى ثقافة الترهات.
So for example,
فعلى على سبيل المثال،
how many of you are washers
كم منكم يغتسل
and how many of you are wipers?
وكم منكم يستخدم الماسحات؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
If, well, I guess you know what I mean.
إذا، حسنا، أعتقد أنكم تعرفون ما أعنيه.
If you're a washer, then you use water
إذا كنتم تغتسلون، ثم تستخدمون المياه
for anal cleansing. That's the technical term.
لتطهير الشرج. هذا هو مصطلح التقني.
And if you're a wiper,
وإذا كنتم تستخدمون المساحة،
then you use toilet paper
ومن ثم ورق التواليت
or, in some regions of the world
أو، في بعض مناطق العالم
where it's not available, newspaper
حيث أنه غير متوفر، صحيفة
or rags or corncobs.
أو الخرق أو عرنوس الذرة.
And this is not just a piece of trivia,
وهذه ليست مجرد معلومات تافهة،
but it's really important to understand
ولكن من المهم حقا أن نفهم
and solve the sanitation problem.
وحل مشكلة الصرف الصحي.
And it is a big problem:
وهذه مشكلة كبيرة:
There are 2.5 billion people in the world
هناك 2.5 مليار شخص في العالم
who don't have access to adequate sanitation.
لا يستطيعون الوصول إلى المرافق الصحية الملائمة.
For them, there's no modern toilet.
بالنسبة لهم، ليس هناك مرحاض حديث.
And there are 1.1 billion people
وهناك 1.1 مليار شخص
whose toilets are the streets
مراحيضهم هي الشوارع
or river banks or open spaces,
أو ضفاف الأنهار أو المساحات المفتوحة،
and again, the technical term for that is
ومرة أخرى، فإن المصطلح التقني لذلك هو
open defecation,
التغوط المفتوح،
but that is really simply
ولكن ببساطة هذا ما يسمي
shitting in the open.
بالتغوط في العراء.
And if you're living in fecal material
وإذا كنت تعيش في المواد البرازية
and it's surrounding you, you're going to get sick.
وكانت محيطة بك، ستصبح مريضًا.
It's going to get into your drinking water,
ستصل إلى مياه الشرب الخاصة بك،
into your food, into your immediate surroundings.
في طعامك، في محيطك فوريًا.
So the United Nations estimates
ولذلك فإن الأمم المتحدة تُقدر
that every year, there are 1.5 million child deaths
أنه في كل عام، هناك 1.5 مليون طفل يموتون
because of inadequate sanitation.
بسبب عدم كفاية المرافق الصحية.
That's one preventable death every 20 seconds,
هذا يمثل وفاة واحدة يمكن إيقافها يمكن إيقافها كل 20 ثانية،
171 every hour,
171 كل ساعة،
4,100 every day.
4100 كل يوم.
And so, to avoid open defecation,
وهكذا، لتجنب التغوط في العراء،
municipalities and cities
على البلديات والمدن
build infrastructure, for example, like pit latrines,
بناء البنية التحتية، على سبيل المثال، مثل المراحيض الجافة،
in peri-urban and rural areas.
في المناطق شبه الحضرية والريفية.
For example, in KwaZulu-Natal province in South Africa,
على سبيل المثال، في مقاطعة كوازولو ناتال في جنوب أفريقيا،
they've built tens of thousands of these pit latrines.
بنيت عشرات الآلاف من هذه المراحيض الجافة.
But there's a problem when you scale up
ولكن هناك مشكلة عند التزايد
to tens of thousands, and the problem is,
إلى عشرات الآلاف، والمشكلة هي،
what happens when the pits are full?
ماذا يحدث عندما تمتلئ المراحيض؟
This is what happens.
هذا ما يحدث.
People defecate around the toilet.
الناس يتبرزون حول المرحاض.
In schools, children defecate on the floors
في المدارس، الأطفال يتبرزون على الارض
and then leave a trail outside the building
ثم يتركون وراءهم أثرًا خارج المبنى
and start defecating around the building,
ويبدأون في التبرز حول المبنى،
and these pits have to be cleaned
ويجب أن يتم تنظيف هذه المراحيض
and manually emptied.
وتُفرغ يدويا.
And who does the emptying?
ومن الذي يقوم بالإفراغ؟
You've got these workers
هناك هؤلاء العمال
who have to sometimes go down into the pits
الذين يجب أن ينزلوا أحيانا إلى أسفل داخل الحفر
and manually remove the contents.
لإزالة المحتويات يدويا.
It's a dirty and dangerous business.
إنه عمل قذر وخطير.
As you can see, there's no protective equipment,
كما ترون، ليست هناك معدات واقية،
no protective clothing.
لا ملابس واقية.
There's one worker down there.
هناك عامل واحد هناك.
I hope you can see him.
آمل أن تتمكنوا من رؤيته.
He's got a face mask on, but no shirt.
يرتدي كمامه على وجهه، ولكن بدون قميص.
And in some countries, like India,
وفي بعض البلدان، مثل الهند،
the lower castes are condemned
الطبقة الدنيا مُدانة
to empty the pits,
بتفريغ الحفر،
and they're further condemned by society.
وهم أيضا مدانون من قبل المجتمع.
So you ask yourself, how can we solve this
لذلك عليك أن تسأل نفسك، كيف يمكننا حل هذه
and why don't we just build Western-style flush toilets
ولماذا لا نبني النمط الغربي من مراحيض المزود بمياه الصرف
for these two and a half billion?
لهؤلاء الاثنين ونصف المليار؟
And the answer is, it's just not possible.
والجواب هو، هو فقط غير ممكن.
In some of these areas, there's not enough water,
في بعض من هذه المناطق، ليس هناك ما يكفي من المياه،
there's no energy,
ليست هناك طاقة،
it's going to cost tens of trillions of dollars
سوف تكلف عشرات التريليونات من الدولارات
to lay out the sewer lines
لمد خطوط الصرف الصحي
and to build the facilities
وبناء المرافق
and to operate and maintain these systems,
وتشغيل وصيانة هذه الأنظمة،
and if you don't build it right,
وإذا كنت لا تبني بالشكل الصحيح،
you're going to have flush toilets
ستكون لدينا مراحيض
that basically go straight into the river,
التي تصرف أساسا مباشرة في النهر،
just like what's happening in many cities
تماما مثل ما يحدث في العديد من المدن
in the developing world.
في العالم النامي.
And is this really the solution?
وهل هذا حقا هو الحل؟
Because essentially, what you're doing is
لأنه أساسا، ما تفعلونه هو
you're using clean water
أنكم تستخدمون مياها نظيفة
and you're using it to flush your toilet,
وتستخدمونها لصرف المرحاض الخاص بك،
convey it to a wastewater treatment plant
ناقلًا إياه إلى محطة معالجة مياه الصرف الصحي
which then discharges to a river,
الذي تُصرف في النهر،
and that river, again, is a drinking water source.
وهذا النهر، مرة أخرى، مصدر مياه الشرب.
So we've got to rethink sanitation,
لذلك علينا أن نعيد التفكير الصرف الصحي،
and we've got to reinvent the sanitation infrastructure,
وعلينا إعادة اختراع البنية التحتية للصرف الصحي،
and I'm going to argue that to do this,
وعلي القول بأنه للقيام بذلك،
you have to employ systems thinking.
علينا توظيف نظم التفكير.
We have to look at the whole sanitation chain.
علينا أن ننظر إلى سلسلة الصرف الصحي الكاملة.
We start with a human interface,
نبدأ بالجانب البشري،
and then we have to think about how feces
ومن ثم علينا أن نفكر في كيفية
are collected and stored,
تجميع وتخزين المخلفات،
transported, treated and reused —
ونقلها ومعالجتها وإعادة استخدامها -
and not just disposal but reuse.
وليس فقط التخلص منها لكن إعادة استخدامها.
So let's start with the human user interface.
إذا دعونا نبدأ مع واجهة المستخدم البشرية.
I say, it doesn't matter if you're a washer or a wiper,
أقول، لا يهم إذا كنت مغتسلا أو مساحا،
a sitter or a squatter,
جالسا أو ثانيا ركبتيك،
the human user interface should be clean
ينبغي أن تكون واجهة المستخدم البشرية نظيفة
and easy to use, because after all,
وسهلة الاستخدام، لأنه بعد كل شيء،
taking a dump should be pleasurable.
التفريغ يجب أن يكون ممتعا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And when we open the possibilities
وعندما نفتح الاحتمالات
to understanding this sanitation chain,
لفهم سلسلة الصرف الصحي تلك،
then the back-end technology,
ثم التكنولوجيا النهائية،
the collection to the reuse, should not really matter,
التجميع لإعادة الاستخدام، لا ينبغي أن يهم حقا،
and then we can apply
ومن ثم يمكننا تطبيق
locally adoptable and context-sensitive solutions.
حلول مقبولة محليًا وحساسة السياق.
So we can open ourselves to possibilities like,
حتى نتمكن من فتح لأنفسنا احتمالات مثل،
for example, this urine-diverting toilet,
على سبيل المثال، هذا المرحاض المحول للبول،
and there's two holes in this toilet.
وهناك فتحتان في هذا المرحاض.
There's the front and the back,
هناك الأمامية والخلفية،
and the front collects the urine,
والامامية تجمع البول،
and the back collects the fecal material.
والخلفية تجمع المواد البرازية.
And so what you're doing is you're separating the urine,
وما تفعلونه هو فصل البول،
which has 80 percent of the nitrogen
والذي يحتوي على 80 في المئة من النيتروجين
and 50 percent of the phosphorus,
و50 في المئة من الفوسفور،
and then that can then be treated
ويمكن بعد ذلك معالجته
and precipitated to form things like struvite,
ويتكثر ليشكل شيئًا كالستروفيت،
which is a high-value fertilizer,
وهو سماد ذو قيمة عالية،
and then the fecal material can then be disinfected
ثم يمكن بعد ذلك تعقيم المواد البرازية
and again converted to high-value end products.
وتحويلها مرة أخرى إلى منتجات ذات قيمة عالية.
Or, for example, in some of our research,
أو، على سبيل المثال، في بعض أبحاثنا،
you can reuse the water by treating it
يمكنك إعادة استخدام المياه من خلال معالجتها
in on-site sanitation systems
في أنظمة صرف صحي فورية
like planter boxes or constructed wetlands.
مثل صناديق الزرع أو الأراضي الرطبة المشيدة.
So we can open up all these possibilities
إذا فأنه يمكننا أن نفتح كل هذه الاحتمالات
if we take away the old paradigm of flush toilets
إذا استبعدنا النموذج القديم من المراحيض
and treatment plants.
ومحطات المعالجة.
So you might be asking, who's going to pay?
إذا قد تتسأل، من الذي سيدفع؟
Well, I'm going to argue that governments
حسنا، أنا ذاهب إلى القول بأن الحكومات
should fund sanitation infrastructure.
يجب أن تُمول البنية التحتية للصرف الصحي.
NGOs and donor organizations,
المنظمات غير الحكومية والمنظمات المانحة،
they can do their best, but it's not going to be enough.
يمكن أن تفعل أفضل ما لديها، لكنه لن يكون كافيا.
Governments should fund sanitation
الحكومات يجب أن تمول الصرف الصحي
the same way they fund roads
بنفس الطريقة التي يمولون بها الطرق
and schools and hospitals
والمدارس والمستشفيات
and other infrastructure like bridges,
وغيرها من البنى التحتية مثل الجسور،
because we know, and the WHO has done this study,
لأننا نعرف، وقد قامت منظمة الصحة العالمية بهذه الدراسة،
that for every dollar that we invest
أنه مقابل كل دولار يستثمر
in sanitation infrastructure,
في البنية التحتية للصرف الصحي،
we get something like three to 34 dollars back.
نربح في المقابل من ثلاثة إلى 34 دولارًا.
Let's go back to the problem of pit emptying.
دعونا نعد لمشكلة إفراغ الُحفر.
So at North Carolina State University,
في جامعة ولاية كارولينا الشمالية
we challenged our students to come up with a simple solution,
تحدينا طلابنا للتوصل إلى حل بسيط،
and this is what they came up with:
وهذا هو ما جاؤوا به:
a simple, modified screw auger
مثقاب حلزوني معدل، بسيط
that can move the waste up
والذي يمكنه إزالة المخلفات
from the pit and into a collecting drum,
من الحفرة إلى برميل تجميع،
and now the pit worker
والآن عامل الحفرة
doesn't have to go down into the pit.
ليس عليه أن يذهب إلى أسفل داخل الحفرة.
We tested it in South Africa, and it works.
اختبرناه في جنوب أفريقيا، وأنه نجح.
We need to make it more robust,
نحن بحاجة لجعله أكثر قوة،
and we're going to do more testing
وسنجري مزيدا من الفحوصات
in Malawi and South Africa this coming year.
في مالاوي وجنوب أفريقيا العام القادم،
And our idea is to make this
فكرتنا هي جعل هذا
a professionalized pit-emptying service
خدمة إفراغ حفر احترافية
so that we can create a small business out of it,
حتى نتمكن من إنشاء مشروع صغير منها،
create profits and jobs,
لخلق الأرباح وفرص العمل،
and the hope is that,
والأمل هو أنه،
as we are rethinking sanitation,
كما أننا نعيد النظر في الصرف الصحي،
we are extending the life of these pits
نحن نمد أعمار هذه الحفر
so that we don't have to resort
حتى لا نضطر إلى اللجوء
to quick solutions
لحلول سريعة
that don't really make sense.
التي ليس لها حقا معنى.
I believe that access to adequate sanitation
وأعتقد أن الوصول إلى صرف صحي مناسب
is a basic human right.
هو حق أساسي من حقوق الإنسان.
We need to stop the practice
نحن بحاجة إلى وقف ممارسة جعل
of lower castes and lower-status people
الطبقات الدنيا والناس الأقل وضعا
going down and being condemned to empty pits.
ينزلون وهم مجبرون على إفراغ الحفر.
It is our moral, it is our social
إنه من واجبنا الاخلاقي والاجتماعي
and our environmental obligation.
والبيئي.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)